Il ruolo della casa è che parliamo in inglese, ma chi vuole parlare in italiano è permesso
di farlo, anche perché c'è, non so se c'è interpretazione.
Does this mean that there is interpretation, direttore?
Okay, just not to get emotional. Well, today we discuss here the primaries,
and the occasion is given to us by the fact that the author of a book on the USA elections
and political system, Donatella Campus and Gianfranco Pasquino, are here with us.
So it's a wonderful opportunity for us to dig into one of the most intriguing sort of
processes of western democracies, which is the primaries in the US, basically.
We Italians look at the primaries with a sort of mixed feeling. We like them, but we fear them.
Not the American ones, but the idea of having primaries in this country as well.
Gianfranco is a supporter of the primaries. Politician is not a real politician, he was
in parliament for a few years, but without really being affected in the sense that he
has remained what he was, which I appreciate. Because primaries, on the one side difficult
to control, on the other side may be controlled by somebody. And these opposite reasons are
enough to make several politicians wary of them. If I'm not sure that I can control them,
why should I want to undergo such a complicated process of selection of candidates?
At the same time, they require a sort of cultural tradition that perhaps we lack in this country.
We may learn something. At the same time, when we read about the history of the primaries in the US,
we also have voices that say that before the primaries it was worse, but perhaps it was also better.
And we know everything also about this thing. But whatever we think about the primaries,
the fact remains that as we see them from outside, it's a sort of vital process of democracy.
This is undeniable. Because the main issues that a country has to decide upon by the following elections
come out, are debated. Candidates are forced to take a standing on them, opposing to each other,
and you can understand how they really think, whether they are consistent or not,
what they said in the past, what they are saying now, etc. And in terms of understanding by the citizens
of what is topical for the political arena in that precise moment of history,
while it's a wonderful kind of instrument to spread around issues and to understand
whether something is more important than something else. Of course, there is an aspect that has to be considered.
I suppose that in Malta or in Latvia or in Slovenia they would be much less expensive than they are in a big country.
And therefore you have this kind of profile of our democracies in the big countries that has to be somehow reflected upon.
How much does it cost to be a candidate first in the primaries and then in the electoral process afterward?
How the money is collected? Where does the money come from? Does it affect the freedom of the candidates
and afterwards of the elected officials? So in my view this is also something that we should consider,
the cost of democracy in other words. But that's why it's a very mixed process,
because it is essential for the citizens to understand, it is essential to have money to allow citizens to understand.
And the former aspect is something that strengthens democracy,
the latter aspect might be something that weakens democracy. So I mean it's a very interesting topic to discuss.
I've used my time even more than I should. You are one, two, three, four, five. If you remain...
...through November, precinct captains to organize each of those 3,000 precincts.
And they have 3,000 team leaders who are volunteers that work with those paid precinct captains.
So they're paying attention to the fight. They know the same 17 states and the same 3,000 precincts within those states,
that one or two percent of the votership that will decide this election.
So it's going to be a very tough election and I would predict it will be a very close election.
And as I argued recently in an op-ed in the Washington Post, which some of you may have read,
we could very well, and I'll make this my closing point before they throw me out,
we could very well have a situation because of our electoral system and its electoral college
where you have to win the votes in the series of the provinces of the states.
Where Bush wins again without winning the popular vote and is sent back for four more years
even though he comes in second in the national popular vote.
And because the elections are so close, and Claudio and I agree, I think we are on the cusp of what's called a new party system
because in such turmoil and imbalance out of that normally comes a party system
when it's very divided and our country is very divided and divisive.
It could also go the other way. It could be that Kerry loses the popular vote
but gets his votes in the right combination of states to win the electoral college
and Bush leaves under the same conditions that he arrived.
So watch for something interesting, magical, perhaps tragic to happen in November.
And on that note, I guess I'm definitely out of time. Thank you.
Thank you. It was very exciting, ABB.
But this may happen anywhere.
Wherever you have a majoritarian system where the vote is highly concentrated,
you might have a candidate that scores more votes but fewer seats.
So in the UK it has happened frequently.
I want to tell you something about fundraising and President Bush.
Because when I was in New York days ago I saw a letter that he sent to all the families
having a flat in Fifth Avenue.
Let's hope so.
It's here, 50 meters deep.
Get out before going home.
It's better not to find it, it creates expectations.
It's a risk, but tomorrow they'll forget it.
I think there will be questions because the theme is too exciting.
Ranieri, Ambassador Pallarini.
And the microphone, if you wait a second.
Thank you very much.
È stata menzionata varie volte da varie autori la specialità americana,
la specialità della democrazia americana.
Ora, io so che Giuliano Amato è nato come costituzionalista,
quindi ho un po' paura di dire quello che dico ora.
Cioè che quello che è speciale, più che l'abito costituzionale,
il sistema, le primaries, gli equilibri fra i vari poteri,
perdono disponibilità a svolgere quel ruolo
che tecnicamente si chiama socializzazione politica.
Questo è il discorso sul capitale sociale.
Cioè se i cittadini non si associano fra di loro
si riduce, si erode un po' il tessuto democratico.
Questo è il vero problema americano,
perché se poi andiamo a vedere l'associabilità dei francesi è molto bassa,
l'associabilità degli italiani è alquanto bassa
e in Europa soltanto in un certo senso i paesi dell'Europa centrosettentrionale
hanno un'alta sociabilità, spesso collegata fra l'altro alla pratica religiosa,
che come sappiamo negli Stati Uniti continua a essere un elemento molto forte della sociabilità.
L'ultimo punto è una semplice battuta,
perché noi nel frattempo abbiamo deciso che non demonizziamo i candidati politici,
ma abbiamo deciso che ABB vuol dire amato before Berlusconi.